[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net se radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software hi I'm Priyanka Ragin for
software engineering radio and today I'm
chatting with epek osaya a principal
researcher and technical director of
engineering elligence software systems
group at the seci at kagi melon on the
topic Genai for software
architecture epex research interests
include developing techniques for
improving software development
efficiency and system Evolution with an
emphasis on software architectural
practices software economics and
managing technical dech she has also
co-authored a book on managing technical
dead so welcome to the show epek thanks
a lot for having me Priyanka especially
for a topic that is very exciting given
all the things going on in software
engineering and AI these days yeah I'm
really looking forward to it and before
we jump into it I wanted to set the
context by asking you a question on what
are the key elements needed to define a
software architecture so this is a very
good place to start especially now even
the term architecture is being
overloaded with model architecture
software architecture and system
architecture the way we Define software
architecture has been at the software
engineering Institute for the past two
decades and more it's a way to reason
about different levels of abstraction so
we Define it as the software
architecture of a system is the set of
the structures needed to reason about
the system that comprises the software
elements relationships among them and
the properties of both I gave you the
textbook definition what this means is
you need to think about the structuring
of the the behavior of the system from
different perspectives for example how
the code elements are structured
together and how they relate to each
other is one perspective one structure
which we call modu structures how the
software runs at runtime how it
interacts with different external
systems is the runtime Behavior
component connector structures and
that's another perspective of the system
and then how the system is deployed
distribute deployment and where things
run globally or locally and whatnot is
another perspective which is the
deployment View so reing when we say
software elements you look at the
elements from different perspectives how
they interact with each other either in
modu time and run time or deployment
time so that's what makes the software
architecture how you define those
Elements which is very important but
those are just the maybe the boxes how
they communicate with each other their
relationships and the message exchanges
and all the dependencies are also very
critical so that totality is the
software architecture of a system we
love the boxes and line diagrams or
expressing them but that's only one
perspective of it we might sometimes
forget the other perspectives and that's
what we base align how we talk about
software architecture when we talk about
especially large scale systems okay
that's an impressive answer and so I
would have to ask you now what are like
say the routin tasks which are involved
in architecting because the cases we see
where gen is used is typically in terms
of automation so there are there a
routine tasks in architecture or
architecting I think this is an
excellent question what are the roles
and responsibilities of a software
architect and it of course varies right
there's definitely being able to Define
that software structure and behavior and
the requirements that drive it what is
your context and how you're implementing
it which is the hands- on the keyboard
for the implementation and how it
relates to the abstractions that is one
aspect but there are also all kinds of
other roles and responsibilities of a
software architect in terms of
collecting requirements documenting the
key decisions interacting with
stakeholders in terms of documenting the
requirements understanding the context
there are all kinds of maybe not
necessarily Hands-On implementation
related tasks there are the
communication information gathering and
decision- making tasks so let's put
those aside for a moment because our
topic is Automation and gen so let's
focus on the tooling and what it means
in terms of a software architect's role
and responsibilities and tooling when it
comes to especially the explosion of
tools that we're seeing with the
generative AI so there is the decision-
making and requirements to architecture
decisions one aspect of the architect's
roles and responsibilities what is the
knowledge that you're driving from where
does that knowledge exist some of it is
routine knowledge like design patterns
architectural knowledge other similar
systems the legacy of the system that
has been there for a while that you need
to take into account because what has
been implemented drives your set of next
decisions it creates the context it
creates the constraints that you need to
drive with so understanding the current
system is definitely a key
responsibility of the architect
understanding where the key
architecturally significant requirements
are implemented within the system what
elements of the system really comprise
those implementations is also another
key responsibility of the architect
deciding how responsibilities are
brought together and encapsulating into
software elements is a responsibility of
the architect and of course most
importantly how does the implemented
system conform to the architecture and
how that evolves together is a
responsibility of the architect and the
team of course because this is not
necessarily a one person responsibility
so when it comes to the tooling there
are quite a number of tools that might
be available to the architect but at the
end of the day what we're seeing with
Gen is really implementation driven
tasks where like how do we generate
code structures and methods and classes
or what notot implementation structures
but we're forgetting the design of the
system we're forgetting the structure
and behavior of the system because of
the excitement of the scope of the tasks
this doesn't mean it will not relate to
the design and Architectural aspects
what it means however is we need to step
back and think about what are some of
the tasks that are automatable for
example code summarization is one
knowledge extraction is another one
generating different kinds of
implementation constructs maybe test
cases and code repair these are all
aspects of the system and they relate to
the design and structure and behavior
but I think we're more focused on the
generation implementation code
generation part not necessarily relating
it to the structure and behavior
abstractions so and how does it relate
to the roles and responsibilities it's
the architect's role to do that
conformance and use required tools to be
able to evolve the system based on the
architectural decisions and the
evolution of the system okay that's uh
brilliant I think we we'll probably Deep
dive into a lot of those areas that
you've alluded to but one of the things
that I wanted to ask you here was when
you talk about the conformance to the
architecture then what's the gap between
you know your abstractions turning into
reality oh this is in fact I think the
probably multiple decades long issue
that the Architects and the challenge of
the architects in not AR software
Engineers face because the abstractions
are communicated with different tools
right you communicate the abstraction in
fact sometimes in the earlier days of
the agile they were communicated with
metaphors abstractions are communicated
with high level diagrams context
diagrams uml diagrams whatever diagrams
that are fit for your purpose whereas
when you're implementing it you're
really talking about lines of code
methods or any of those abstractions
could be encapsulated in Frameworks
libraries and whatnot the Gap starts
opening when the traceability from your
architectural decisions are lost into
your implementation especially when the
architecture is not talking the
vocabulary of the details like the
design patterns and tactics help that
vocabulary for example if I'm talking
about a publish subscribe approach then
I could say okay I have publish elements
I have subscribe elements my publish
elements will have particular methods
those methods need to be implemented
here are the signatures of those methods
versus subscribe elements and whatnot so
that level of detail then starts driving
the implementation as well it's when we
are staying at the very highest level
abstractions then we lose that then the
Gap starts happening another way the Gap
starts happening is you have the
implemented system you're evolving the
system from the codebase rather than
evolving the system from the
architecture and we to this state we do
not have tools that help us speak both
languages in the same toolbase and
because of that software engineering
need to have that translation between
those of course many of these repeatable
structures are now implemented within
Frameworks they're part of our tool
chain that helps incorporate some of the
known good architectural decisions into
our systems because they might be just
coming up in terms of these open source
libraries Frameworks tools elements but
when you have the domain specific ones
then you start losing that Gap and
that's how that Gap happens if you're
evolving the architecture but not
evolving the system or vice Versa or
you're not necessarily recognizing that
the system evolved in the way that
needed to be represented in the
architecture so I I think that's again a
wonderful answer to show the gaps and it
took me back to the original reason for
having this talk which was on based on
the article that you WR which was like
can architecture knowledge guide
software development with generative Ai
and there you us the term and you know
it hit me so hard you called some of the
Ivory Tower
Architects so the question I wanted to
ask you here before we Deep dive is do
you think the Ivory Tower Architects
could that problem be resolved with
something like gen because now they're
able to see those potential code the
question you're asking is a fundamental
question I think in terms of how we
develop and evolve and sustain systems
which is there is the very high level
knowledge that you might make decisions
at your corner based on whatever inputs
and then there's the reality qu ity of
the day-to-day
implementation the technology changing
Hardware changing your user base
changing and the teams need to react to
those they do not have the time to
coordinate with many of the stakeholders
that needed to be coordinated so it's
the individuals every single developer
first of all has to understand
architectural abstractions and be
responsible some of it what we're facing
with generative AI tools is both an
opportunity and a risk let me talk about
the opportunity first you talk about the
Ivory Tower architects who might know
all these grandio knowledge in terms of
okay architectural patterns tactics
quality attribute scenarios and some of
those details at the level that they're
exposed to but not maybe always exposed
to the developers now when we have these
tools all that knowledge is in fact easy
to be incorporated into the tools
because they're text they're out there
and the existing large language models
can actually digest that information and
you can query okay what do you mean by a
published subscriber and can you please
show me an example of it that
interactive mode with some of these
tools that we're seeing even with the
chat tools will allow the knowledge to
be transferred so that's the positive
side and there are particular kinds of
trade-offs that you might say okay what
might be some of the Alternatives that
you would pick solve a particular design
challenge or an implementation challenge
so knowledge sharing could actually be
improved with the tools that are
emerging so that's the positive side the
PO potential risk is especially when
we're using these tools for
implementation tasks we're interacting
with those tools with a limited scope
although the moment I say this things
are improving we know the tool Space is
really really evolving in a very
fast-paced way but we're not necessarily
thinking about the entire system how the
entire system is really implemented am I
incorporating the implementation
question that I asked in the same way
with the rest of the system is it
consistently done isn't taking into
account some of the concerns that might
be coming from architectural significant
scenarios and so on and those are things
that we're only now seeing some of the
questions being asked because the
excitement have maybe leveled a little
bit now we see a lot of tools out there
that are helping different kinds of
roles and stakeholders in terms of
interacting with those tools so I think
that's where we will see the Ivory Tower
Architects maybe less because now the
tools will have a little bit more power
and that interaction will be improved
and I would like to also emphasize here
is the tools are not one all and and all
every single individual wherever they
interacted whether they are the model
developers data collectors or any of the
individuals that might be residing in
co-pilots and birds or wherever they are
in the tool chain I guess food chain
they are recognizing that the advances
of generative AI tools is a human AI
partnership the responsibility is on the
user to take take advantage of these
tools while the tools will take some of
the burden off the user's shoulders so
it's an important that we recognize it's
a human AI partnership what does that
say from the perspective of the
architect is or the software engineer
who's using these tools how do I guide
the tool with my expertise so that I can
actually get the right answer how do I
craft my prompt so that it includes some
of the design vocabulary and how do I
judge the response in terms of the
evaluation that it will be fit for my
purpose for whatever task that I'm
trying to address very interesting so I
was just wondering if we could maybe
wrap this introduction part with another
question which is to ask you like some
typical use cases where geni is used for
architectural activities so first of all
I think we need to be honest with
ourselves we're really really in the
very very early stages of these tools
being investigated for more complex
tasks I call architecture a complex task
because the workflow involves multiple
steps that's why I call it a complex
task you need to be able to also
interact with a larger scope within the
system so because of that we're seeing
only now some of the investigations
emerging but some common scenarios
obviously architecture documentation is
one either summarize this document for
me help me document this particular part
of the system generate an API and all
those kinds of of things are very
straightforward tasks code summarization
to help understand what you're looking
at in terms of understanding the context
is another one that helps in terms of
the roles and responsibilities we talked
about architecture knowledge sharing
again you could ask all kinds of
architectural knowledge in terms of okay
how do I implement this particular
framework what does using a I use pops
up before pops up architectural pattern
means for this particular system what
are other similar system systems that I
can learn from these are all very high
level questions that you could take
advantage of with these models the more
interesting ones that are you also
emerging are of course the software
Evolution ones how do I re architect the
system how do I translate from one
programming language to another while
also re architecting and changing the
structure and the behavior of the system
these are more complex because only
generative AI tools will not address
these you'll have to have other tools
within the system but it's also requires
more research and more development of
the tools to be able to address these
more complex workflows okay great I
think we probably like maybe Deep dive
into both of these cases in the next
section and before I want to Deep dive I
also wanted to ask you a question which
I keep seeing in the literature where
they talk about you know different
models like the Gans which is the
generator adversarial networks then the
variational auto and flers and then
recurrent Neo Networks they always in a
lot of the papers I see or even articles
I see they say that the results are
quite better with each model do you have
any take on that so this is where I
think the architecture 101 answer
applies it depends okay and it's really
important because one of the things like
yes some models perform others than
others and in fact just yesterday GPT 40
came out and yes it's faster in some
tasks but there are also some even very
quick experimentation coming out saying
yes they're faster but they're not
always as accurate so these are all
tradeoffs I think it's important to
recognize that these trade-offs will
change it would be very difficult for me
to create a very Broadband okay one
particular sign kind of models are
better than the other one there are but
it's important maybe let's go back and
step back in terms of what are our goals
in terms of these models some of the
questions are are they trained with the
relevant information that we would like
to extract from for example if our goal
is to use a brand new version of a
particular library or framework even if
the model might perform better in some
tasks if there's not trained with that
knowledge it will not perform well the
other one is whether the scope window is
able to address the scope of the
question that I'm asking so that's
another one does it have the interaction
mode in terms of how I'm able to input
the prompts and whether it's able to
process those prompts so those are some
of the ways I think I would evaluate
these from and that's why there's a lot
of experimentation that goes into it one
of the important aspects of using these
models for some of the software
engineering tasks is the consistency
especially when you're using it for
larger tasks will it consistently give
me the accurate enough response so that
I could actually replicate it for
whatever part of the system that I need
to replicate or if some other software
team member wor to interact with the
same question and same task would they
really get the same response so those
would be some of the evaluation criteria
that I would bring to bear rather than
generalizing one is better than the
other okay that's a good point thanks
for that so let's now Deep dive into
some of the Gen use verses that you
alluded to before the first thing I
wanted to ask is as an architect there's
this concept of an architectural context
to help you make that tradeoff decisions
so can the tooling help here this is
where whether your domain has very
particular
details that is in the public domain or
not comes into play quite a number of
software engineering decisions and
implementation decisions and
architecture decisions are in fact not
necessarily too specifically tight to
The Domain the domain specific parts are
smaller percentage of the overall
systems and that's why we're able to
talk about architecture knowledge
generalizable tactics and patterns or
ways that we're implementing thing with
that said there are particular key
domains especially in machine critical
domains or proprietary domains where you
might need to find tune the models for
your context to be able to address some
of the uh design decisions or address
some of the concerns there so I would
say a significant portion of the
architectural design decisions would be
possible to address at the high level
the question is whether you could put
those in terms of the implementation
constructs throughout the system is one
and whether what information what data
do you need to fine-tune is the other
part of it for example we talked about
new versions of external libraries
coming up as one scenario you might have
really really specific business rules
within your system that drive some of
your architectural decisions and you
might need to fine-tune the models with
those business rules however what that
means is you need to pay attention into
the privacy concerns security concerns
whether any information is leaking
whether some of the public private apis
that utilize that information need to be
taken into account when they're
encapsulated at design decisions so
those are some of the considerations
that you would need to take into account
if those are dominating in the system
then the answer would be no you would
really need to make the trade-off from
the perspective of do I use a publicly
available open and general purpose tool
or do I need to fine-tune these models
for my particular use case so I think
one of the things I forgot to ask you
was this term architecture
knowledge it's some in the public domain
some is in the private domain is that
something that can be defined let's see
how do we Define architecture knowledge
so software architecture knowledge has
several components like first of all
it's been around and vetted over a
number of implementations is one aspect
of the architecture knowledge that it's
generic so there's the architecture
design what are the design elements that
is encapsulated in terms of the
component on their relationships as we
talked about is part of the
architectural knowledge what are some of
the particular decisions like for
example I will not allow a particular
element to communicate with another
element because I'm constraining it for
a security reason maintainability reason
performance reason that's part of the
architectural knowledge any particular
assumptions you're making there are
quite a number of cases where things
work in one context but it wouldn't work
in another context like the deployment
environment for example might be part of
what are the assumptions you're making
and what are some of the contexts that
the particular architectural design
decision is applied it so the totality
of these make the architectural
knowledge but what are some of the
examples all kinds of things that we're
talking about for example API design
different distributed system design
different categories of Design Elements
embedded design these are all
architectural knowledge that are in the
generic that is out there what is
important is how you inst entiate that
knowledge that's when it becomes the
Delta that you're talking about yes I
take a generic architectural knowledge
construct then what it means to put it
in my context are the constraints on my
context the same as the assumptions of
that architectural knowledge that is out
there can any of the existing tools help
me walk through even if they don't give
me the answer can these tools help me
walk through the elements of the process
so that even if the tool does not have
the information maybe it helps me to
collect the information to make the
right choices in terms of how I'm
encapsulating different elements and
making them ready for implementation I
don't know if that addresses your
question I think so I mean I think one
of the things it struck me was also the
fact that every time we kind of set out
on a new architecture for a new
component a lot of the times is we sort
of look at these old software
architecture design documents or things
like that and that's like our
architectural knowledge but often times
I think either one we don't have the
patients to look through that which I
think a lot of people and people just
sort of start fresh and then they end up
with the same problems which was there
in the previous system so I was
wondering if these gen tools could also
help you with that that you can use the
architectural knowledge to mine and then
help you feed your new archit correct so
I think you bring an interesting point
in terms of can we mine variations of
the same maybe construct through
existing systems and come up with maybe
all these space of assumptions and the
constraints we're talking about one of
the things if anybody has fancy then
read any of the pattern oriented
software architecture books and all of
that the first thing they'll recognize
is it is so not formal there's a lot of
well if it's in this particular context
this variation might apply in a
different context this variation might
apply there's a lot of variation in
terms of the Assumption and sometimes
you have to make those break the rules
to be able to make it to to your context
but when are you breaking the rules so
much that it does not apply to the
pattern anymore and what is that design
decision space in terms of the different
rules apply for example for performance
let's pick a oneon-one pattern layered
pattern right in layered pattern the
vanilla rule is each layer is only
communicating with the layer below and
so on and you do not do layer bridging
so that you're actually able to
encapsulate the decisions and whatnot
but if you have a critical performance
concern you say you know what I'm going
to make a particular exception for this
a part uh one particular layer is
allowed to access a different particular
layer okay this is an exception it's
allowed it does not necessarily break it
but that's maybe one particular one
allows so when it gets more complex
these tools can in fact help maybe mine
some of these over time so that you can
okay here are some of the this is the
vanilla way to implement it here are
some of the variations and here are the
trade-offs bottom line in architecture
decision- making and design decision
making is the trade-off
right what is the tradeoff and how do
you understand the trade-offs however
it's very important to remember large
language models generative AI tools uh
Foundation models they are probabilistic
models they do not have the ground truth
the way they work is they select the
next element in sequence based on a
probabilistic reasoning of course all
these more sophisticated models are
mimicking or learning with large data
sources so that they are able to provide
as correct as possible response resp es
but the probabilistic nature does not
change because of that the expertise of
the users is essential it increases the
pace of the user especially the expert
user but it does not necessarily always
guarantee that you always have the 100%
correct response so you need to check
the response you need to understand how
you're checking the response which might
become more complicated with
architectural decisions because we're
talking about all kinds of what if
scenarios we said okay it's based on the
cont text we said it's based on the
tradeoffs we said it requires some of
the technical knowledge of the patterns
and tactics which by itself means
there's no one- siiz fits all which also
puts the responsibility on the users
especially software Architects to be
able to provide the right information in
terms of the prompt and also assess the
outcome for that so maybe that's
something in terms of to keep in mind
when we're looking into how am I making
this domain spe specific to my need and
what kind of fine tuning I need with
that data and whether if I have the data
available to do the fine tuning so this
is of course the the one that we talked
about was the fact um that gen could
help you in articulating or maybe
understanding your design decisions
there's a lot of work as you explained
but another case which I wanted to ask
you um in terms of architecture a lot of
times they also talk about the
architecture mimicking your
organizational behavior and structure
and so if you're coming in as a new
architect to a new organization would
these tools help you also kind of
understand a bit of this so one of the
ways these tools whether it's an
architecture task or any task is they're
really good with text so if you have a
text that is describing the
organizational structure if you have an
architecture document describing it they
could definitely help with the
summarization and helping you navigate
through these whether if you have the
organizational structure and you can
deduct the architecture of the system
from that I would not rely on those
because first of all we know that that
mapping is hypothetically true but that
diverges very quickly as well and we
also know that that's not always the
right way to do because this is in fact
said not always in a good way sometimes
it's a negative way right the
organization structure derives the
system architecture but it shouldn't be
that way because a department doesn't
talk to B Department should not be the
two parts of the system should not be
talking to each other so there are all
these positives and negatives part of
that but underlying in your question is
because such tools are good at
summarization and text any document that
you have could help with bringing users
up to speed but this is applicable to
any role and responsibility that does
not have to be a software architecture
related one at all so having talked a
little bit about the proficiencies these
tools have with text I wanted to ask you
about whether these tools are also good
for producing a good architectural di so
there is in fact some early
investigations in terms of whether you
can produce diagrams or whether you can
study the
diagrams I would yes however I think
these are limited uses of these tools
because a good diagram from my
perspective is bottom line is how are
these tools helping the end result which
is to develop a
executable system that I deploy and then
the users can take advantage of so a
good diagram is a diagram that could
actually be part of a model it could
help round trip engineering with
generating some of the code from the
model or whatnot so from that
perspective we need to go into the
formalisms and whether we're able to use
a probabilistic tool like generative AI
tools for formal reasoning for
generating formal artifacts whether
they're models diagrams and whether
we're able to check whether that
formalism is correct and use it for
other Downstream activities I think
that's really the key question we should
be asking but yes of course they can
generate diagrams you can review the
diagrams there are all kinds of fun
things that you can do with them that's
probably less exciting for me more
exciting is am I able to generate
formalisms formal artifacts because
implementation is Al like code is also a
formal artif or at least there are rules
to it and propagate those rules
consistently so that my goal which is
the executable implemented system is
working in its intended use that's a
very great answer I think it made me
think also because I think the what the
key question is it's it's a
probabilistic model right so that yeah
so we have to yeah we have to remember
it's probabilistic and we also remember
why uml never worked right unified
modeling language I mean yes there are
benefits of it but it never necessarily
because the systems are very big and it
gets overwhelming so the bottom line
question is a large scale system needs
to be represented with different levels
of abstraction without forgetting the
implementation constructs will these
tools help us navigate through different
levels of abstraction
consistently and speed up the process
while taking into account the context
and the experience of the expertise that
is required and I think There's an
opportunity and the opportunity comes
from especially some of the new
approaches that are coming with even co-
pilot has workspaces and workflows to be
able to take advantage of uh generative
AI tools you need to think about the
workflows what is the workflow it could
be a narrow scoped workflow for example
code repair I find a bug I repair that
bug I compile and I deploy it so that's
a n work because the scope of the
mentation is maybe a couple lines of
code you can create rules for it it's
not the space is much maybe more
tractable that's a small workflow but
then a larger workflow is well if it
happens in many places in the system I
can scale it that's again maybe possible
but it starts getting more complicated
well if I have this I could do it in a
particular way or a different way but
that affects my performance how do I
choose one over the other and how do I
propagate that throughout the rest of
the system then you're starting to ask
design questions but that's a large like
that's still a workflow it just have
different tasks within the workflow and
we shouldn't assume that it's only
generative AI tools that will be part of
the workflow other tools might be part
of the tool chain that can be not as
that the developer can utilize without
having have to go between different
tools those could be masked within the
more creative uses of development tools
for software Architects as well as
developers yeah actually this U brings
me took me back down memory Lan because
I I guess the question I was going to
ask you is can geni be good for
producing code that fits the
architecture and I remember like you
know back in the day when I was doing my
masters in CMU we had a similar thing
where we had this the eclipse plugin
which we used to write for all our Java
code we used to have these architectural
design decisions and things you know
written there and we would do that and
then that would produce the code and
that way we would always see what was
the gap between the architecture and
code so like in terms of that in these
gen use cases can architecture be I mean
these tools be good for like producing
code that fits the architecture or even
if the architecture changes can they
refactor the code so I think the within
your question what I'm hearing is how do
we construct The Prompt that represents
the architectural decision so that they
actually perform to it like for example
I would like
to implement
whatever capability but I would like to
make sure that I use a layered pattern
because I might need to extend it and
when you're doing the layered pattern
put particular functionality in a layer
called X put other functionality in a
layer called Y and so on and so forth so
it comes to how the user constructs The
Prompt given the prompt so that's one
step of the way right should the prompt
include all those key Concepts
to drive the generation that's step
number one that's maybe a question and
the question number two is given those
Concepts will the models be able to
structure the response that actually
fits that I think the answer to both are
yes but I think we need to probably get
a little bit more smarter in terms of
what it means to construct that prompt
because within that we're already saying
we need to teach the user the
architecture vocabulary in fact I have
joking say well generative AI tools will
make software architecture cool again
because that make your makes your job
easier rather than interacting with it
method by Method or line by you could
just say I would like to have a I mean
at the very very L could I say I would
like to have a service based system I
have X number of services please
encapsulate these Services as this way
or that way here are some of the
communication constraints VOA it didn't
work okay maybe regenerate and fix that
prompt will that make me faster will it
give me feedback in terms of the
mistakes that I might be making in
encapsulate like communicating my
decisions and how do I check the result
so that's maybe it's the same workflow
but multiple steps are combined together
and that's I think interesting for us to
articulate and maybe think through as we
go through experimenting with these
systems let's all be honest with
ourselves we're still experimenting I
think none of us really no know where
they are really going to change how we
develop
yes we do see some data coming out from
like a productivity improvements this
and that however whether they will
really will will be able to take the
benefits reap the benefits for large
scale system development evolution is an
aspect you ask the refactoring question
I think that's similar there is a lot of
knowledge out there in terms of
refactoring so I think when we look at
it from a narrow scope like for example
I would like you to refactor my long
methods or or insert a method extract
method like there are all these Martin
follow refactoring rules I think those
have potential to work they're already
in other kinds of tools there are search
based there are other AI approaches that
already incorporate some of these I
think from that perspective those
refactoring approaches will be possible
to use with generative AI tools those I
call those more local refactorings when
we talk about large scale refactoring
which comes brings back the architecture
I think the jury is still out there
because that brings back the steps of
the workflow what are the tasks that are
going to happen and how does the change
propagate with the rest of the system I
think for that you still cannot just
rely on gen tools you need to really
take advantage of other tools and
expertise and evaluation and compiling
unit tests and whatnot that come into
the all the good and bad of software
development and software Evolution
that's right absolutely right for more
complex systems yeah I think think you
say it's it's not so trial yeah and you
know it's also we do not have to maybe
use it for every single task we have
that's also important to recognize if
these tools help with code complete
local code repair some generation tasks
that make that part of implementation
faster and more
accurate and quality conformant then the
software Engineers are left with the
time to spend more in terms of the
design than the structure and behavior
or trade-off analysis or whatever they
need to do that require more time and
that trade-off is also not that bad of a
trade-off I am not willing to let go of
potential higher complex use cases yet
but probably it's not one or the the
answer is not one or the other it's
really a combination I think yeah one of
the things in the article that you
talked about I mean that you wrote about
also referen this self testing code with
Martin Fowler and I think it's you how
where they talked about how chart GPT
can be used for you know self testing I
reference that in the show notes when I
was reading that another part of the
while I was very a struck by the self
testing code examples over there I also
noticed this part of the article that
talked about I just to quote it once it
receives enough words in the
conversations it starts forgetting the
earliest material and in effect it makes
it very curiously
forgetful so he talks a lot about the
context and having those strict
tokenization so has that changed as the
technology is gotten better from the
time you wrote the article oh yes I mean
at the time when I wrote These articles
I would have to change it maybe every
week There's a like the reason these
articles were written for I was the
editor-in-chief of I software mag
magzine so there's a timeline I
typically have maybe two months so
between the first week to the third week
okay let's revisit what's changing so
there that was a period of very fast
change We are continuing to see change I
think there are two aspects of we're
seeing change one is the scope window is
larger now you can feed PDF the models
are not multimodel you can feed text as
well as images and voice and whatnot so
that is going to continue to improve the
forgetfulness will also that is related
to the scope window what keeps in mind
and all that that's also going to
improve as well but what is also
changing is specialized tools built on
top of these models so maybe even if the
context window does not improve there
might be other workarounds that help you
keep that context and continue to build
on to the information and you build on
that's one thing that is improving the
other thing that is improving is the
prompt engineering aspect how you
construct prompts so that you're able to
get the results in the way that you
would like in in fact Martin F's article
was the inspiration that resulted me to
think about wait a minute there's more
here going back to the make soft
architectur software architecture will
actually be again important because you
will have to recognize these it's the
kind of knowledge that you feed into the
not only generate the system with these
design constructs but also generate the
tests when you generate the tests you
have to generate the test using these
particular rules so that vocabulary
becomes important important as part of
the recognizing so the tools will
continue to improve but the apps that
are built on top of the models will also
continue to improve as we think about
more complex use cases or more
particular use cases that software
Engineers can take advantage of and I
mean not to mention all the co-pilots
and all of those tools are also
improving by the minute because there's
a lot of excitement as well as potential
in improving our systems through these
tools because if we can write correct
code and assess their design to start
with that's actually quite intriguing in
terms of our overall goal from a
software engineering and system
development perspective I think I want
to move on to this a little bit on the
state of the practice and tooling so
from what I understood from what you
said is a lot of the architectural
knowledge and constructs and elements
have to now they have to like feed this
prompt text and so there'll be this new
area of I don't know what do you say
research or maybe area of study where
you how do you make things better with
your prompt text so do you think a lot
of the tooling will come around that
area there's some generic knowledge that
is already out there in terms of the
prompt patterns how do you construct
prompt patterns this is generic these
prompt patterns apply to any kind of use
case not just software engineering or
software architecture so that's one
class that is already out there in fact
there's already uh work that is coming
out in sharing some patterns in terms of
how to construct prompts for example
work by Vanderbilt University cat GPD
prompt patterns for improving code
quality refactoring requir ustation and
software design share some of the
patterns these patterns are generic
patterns what actually is going to be
the next level is okay when I'm if I
have a particular task this task could
be as I I've been using Code
summarization documentation code repair
as examples what does it mean to
construct a prompt for a particular task
but let's bring it back to our topic
software architectures how do I share
vocabulary that will guide the tool to
address my concern properly will be the
next level of patterns and I do think
there is work to be done there and that
will be coming out as part of the
evolving work like how do I share that
information is that information part of
the model and what not is part of
definitely the improvements that we'll
see in the very near future if not being
developed as we speak but it's also
important to recognize that the prompt
provides part of aspect of it the models
will also continue to improve with the
semantic knowledge and the knowledge of
the how you incorporate the elements of
the patterns within the model and so on
and so forth so those are all I think
we're going to see fast improvements in
both spaces so instead of a software
architecture document you might have a
software prompt document asn't FL so I
would equate prompt with the
requirements than the architecture
document because the prompt provides the
way how am I communicating what I need
from the system and how I get out of
that with so the requirements I in fact
there's a lot of good thought to be done
in terms of how I am expressing my
requirements are there particular ways
that I could improve expressing my
requirements and how are the
architectural significant requirements
are communicated at what level and do
they include the solution or are they
just the requirement because when you're
expressing a requirement there might be
many solutions you're expressing
generate a code you're expressing a
solution so there's that different steps
that you need to take between a end user
requirement or a particular
functionality use case to what it means
to create the implemented space but yes
you're right that's the nature of the
artifact will change eventually might
change that's in fact a good point I had
not thought about that one other thing I
wanted to ask you and this might be
something a bit basic but one of the
things as someone starting off at a you
know as a developer like trying to
figure out whether you know should I go
for a merge sort or a bubble sort or how
should the database design be done if
you have a complex query requirement
these are some things that you actually
run through with your software architect
is this typical questions that you can
ask the Gen now I think these are
questions that not only you can ask but
it actually does pretty well in some of
these established algorithms and
provided again I will complet keep
repeating myself here intentionally it's
a probabilistic technology it will just
pick probabilistically the next one in
fact there are all these parameters that
you set in the tools sometimes so that
it has more variation it might provide
because it might have high probability
hence it might provide a wrong answer
since it's just probab dep picking that
so how you test the outcome is really
important it will generate however I
will say and I think this will probably
be true for anybody who people played
with these tools for whatever reason if
you're are an expert in a particular
task it really improves your ability to
generate results for whatever your task
has especially if you're able to craft
the prompts appropriately I've seen it
work that way very well I think a lot of
developers are excited because code
complete and things these are
technologies that have been already out
there with other techniques it just
really really accelerated their utility
and those are I think important
advancements that now allow us to even
talk about okay may what is our next
more complex task that we can
investigate utilizing these tools so yes
so I think established algorithms and
their ability to help you yes with a
caveat you have to test it you cannot
just rely on it because of the
probabilistic nature of the tools what
are things that you should watch out for
can gen reduce the creativity or
innovation of an
architect maybe so there are several
areas to pay attention to one is the
data that these tools are trained with
so after a while it gets not maybe
repetitive is not the best way to
express it but you get what you put into
it right if you have so you're getting
the solutions that it was generated so
creativity
requiring tasks May risk it however if
we're talking about giving a solution to
an existing problem we are already
talking about repetitive Solutions so
maybe the risk is here not that high
however let's look at the other side if
it's trained with bad examples because
all the examples we have out there are
open source examples examples that
people are willing to share or
incomplete
examples that is really where the risk
is is the training Corpus really
completed with correct and well
constructed and good examples to provide
you the correct answer and I think this
is a community effort in a way it's
going to continue to improve I'm really
hoping the developers of the models are
working in the background improving some
of these and cleaning their data and
whatnot so that's really where the risk
resides the other one is like if you're
getting is it circular and you're
injecting the same mistake back in and
so forth so those are probably the
mistakes to watch out for for creativity
requiring areas or tasks which are I
might get yes there is some creativity
in software architecture but I would
want to believe that correctness and fit
for
purpose is a little higher up than
creativity maybe there is some
creativity there but we're not talking
about artistic creativity here we're
talking about ability to answer
particular significant specific
requirements so I don't know whether it
matters we have a different solution at
all the time or the same solution works
so that's maybe every organization every
individual might have a different
opinion on that I think that's really
well answered I'll keep in mind the
probabilistic nature of the answers so I
think that is very important for all of
us listening to the show it is very
important and in fact Let me give
another important reference for the
listeners there is an ACM article done
by Microsoft colleagues who looked into
some of the early outcomes of using
co-pilot by developers and one of the
things that they realize is it does not
replace expertise it actually shines a
light on the expertise what that means
is if I'm an expert in a particular area
I would very quickly be able to
understand that the answer that the tool
is giving me is wrong or I would know
how to ask the question correctly so
that I get the right answer so that's
really important in terms of the uses
with the tools that's why human AI
partnership is something now everybody
recognizes it's not replacement for the
skills no software Engineers will not go
out of business however how we develop
expertise how we develop different
skills evaluation skills critical
thinking skills Quick verification and
validation skills become important in
utilizing these tools whether you're a
software architect software engineer
software tester wherever you sit on the
fot chain of software development like
cycle these are important tasks to
skills to develop interesting so now I
have to ask you the next question being
from security background what are the
security implications like
misinformation data leakage from using
these gen tools when you're designing or
architecting systems so absolutely a
concern and in fact because of that we
see limited experimentation in some
domains and some organizations by these
tools these are absolutely concerns
especially what we don't know although
developers of the models have
disclosures whether they're using or not
to some of the data that is being input
once you start interacting especially
with the public models you're
interacting with that domain and your
your information becomes part of the
public domain so that is a concern from
an architectural perspective it might
create potential risks in terms of what
is being exposed whether that data is
being utilized for other parts of the
system or whether that data now is being
trained within that overall public area
I mean early on we all read about the
Samsung case where the developers
utilize use proprietary information in
and fed the code into the tool because
one of the use cases is okay here's my
code do x or y z or with them so that's
also becomes a risk so I think the risk
is not just the data leakage and
security it's really any proprietor
information that you would give into it
and I think the users it's on the users
to be careful rather than on the I mean
yes of course there's a responsibility
of the tools but I would air on the side
of assuming the worst from the tools and
until we're sure or whether we and we're
able to take precautions and then
provide the information that is more
proprietary or secur to risks that's
that's one aspect of the security the
other aspect of the security of course
the implementations right whether it's
giving the correct answer or not again
the to code specific tools are improving
because these concerns are critical
concerns but that doesn't mean it's like
perfect errors will leak in I think
that's interesting because the question
I had next was as a user of these geni
tools there's a certain lack of
transparency on the output produced
because you don't really understand how
AI model comes at you know delivers a
particular output it can be a bit
difficult to understand because of the
complexity and therefore it's easy to
check the correctness for code but how
do you check the correctness for
architecture you talked a little bit
about the correctness being of most
importance so what do you do in that
case so I think we need to focus on the
artifact that is being generated I I I
like how you phrase that question from
that perspective Pian what is the
artifact being generated so how do I
check code tests walkthroughs code
review all those kinds of techniques so
we need to ask ourselves how do we check
correctness of the architecture which
probably we don't I mean yeah we do
qualitative architecture reviews and all
that but that's I think brings up a gap
in our softare architecture practice so
we need to think about how do we check
the correctness of an architecture
design decision to start with which is
mostly qualitative techniques expertise
based techniques okay if you're using
some formal techniques maybe if you're
implementing the system the system
becomes the reality and all of that so
that's I don't think is on the geni
tools at all that's on our software
architecture practice how do we check
the correctness of an architecture
decision how do we check the correctness
of a tradeoff which is why it becomes
more of this fuzzy high level
conversation often but again we can
resort to some of the the devil is in
the details in fact Paul Clemens who is
one of the authors of the software
architecture documentation and software
architect principles and practices books
from the software engineering Institute
has always emphasized that software
architecture is a very detailed practice
we always think it's very high level in
boxes and diagrams so if we have those
details then we are able to actually
think about okay how do I check those
details so I think that's really where
the question is I don't think that's on
we cannot blame J and probabilistic
models for
that I would love to but it's fair
enough so then I guess I should end the
show by asking you the last question
which is what are then the future Trends
in the space and how do you see it
growing so I think it's a very exciting
time for automated tool development this
is probably where we'll see the future
developments as we are understanding of
how to use the tools improves the models
will improve as the models will improve
we'll slowly expand our use cases we'll
get more confidence in some tasks and
we'll have less confidence others so I
think the key question is how do we
avoid focusing on the small tasks that
might risk the overall structure and
behavior of the system and are there
ways to ensure that some of the
architectural concerns are part of the
I'll say conversation for lack of a
better word interaction maybe that's
better interaction of the tools and what
are some some of the capabilities that
need to be incorporated in these tools
to be able to bring design knowledge
into them is probably where and start
small and go from there is probably the
right way to do it okay we've done some
of the more implementation small scope
implementation specific tasks now what
is the next level what is the smallest
design construct that we can experiment
with and that might help us look into it
there are other ones that are being
utilized I mentioned a couple that we're
working on like for example how do I
upgrade known libraries using some of
these tools again gen is not only tool
there are other tools that are out there
but they are small enough and complex
enough to experiment with these co-pilot
came up with the workspace and workflow
kind of an approach and that's also
going to be I think so we'll see those
kinds of more complex use cases being
experimented with I think that's one way
we'll see being able to provide data
quickly into the Corpus as new versions
of tools are coming out Frameworks
libraries and all those that's also
another area that's that's on tools
anyway on the models anyways and then
one aspect that is probably important is
to recognize that it's important to
continue to develop expertise rather
than assume that the tool takes care of
it that's probably where we'll have to
continue to remind ourselves thank you
very much be I think a lot of your
answers was spoken in a way that it also
reminded us of what is important to do
as well so I think think apart from the
aspect of exploring geni tools it's also
maybe for us to reflect a bit on what
things we should do bit better so thank
you for that and also I think we forget
we get all excited there's a new
technology we're all very excited what
is the goal we're trying to accomplish
is has to come always first I think
that's important and sometimes it's
difficult to admit but maybe existing
tools are good enough in some cases I'm
not suggesting that but it's really the
combination of the tools yes gen will I
think help improve and I do believe what
I say the generative AI tools will shine
the light on software architecture in
ways that we had not recognized before
because at the end of the day it's not
this small scoped class or method or
whatever the scope is that we're
developing it's the system we're
developing how do I develop the system
rather than the small experimentation
that we're dealing with currently point
taken thank you very much well thank you
for having me and I think one thing that
I need to ask you is what is the best
way that people can reach you if they
want to get in touch email LinkedIn
LinkedIn LinkedIn maybe or email me I
will add both in our show notes and
thanks once again thanks for coming on
the show thank you thanks for listening
this is Priyanka Ragan for software
engineering
radio thanks for listening to SC radio
an educational program brought to you by
It software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at
e-r. to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack Channel at seo.
slack.com you can also email us at
team-
radio.net this and all other episodes of
SE radio is licensed under Creative
Commons license
2.5 thanks for listening